

PERSONAL SUMMARY

Ahmed Saud Ahmed Al Shali

Health, Safety and Environment (HSE) Specialist, Occidental of Oman Al Seeb 903, Way 7585, House 10093 Muscat, Sultanate of Oman E: Ahmed11hse@hotmail.com M: + 968 95266759

Self-motivated, capable, tenacious, and pragmatic. Able to use own initiative and work as part of a team. Certified International General Certificate in Occupational Health & Safety (NEBOSH IGC) with 14 years' experience in Health, Safety and Environment in Oil & Gas and other fields including Operations and Heavy Industries. Holding bachelor's degree in *Process Engineering* from Caledonian Collage of Engineering, Joined Occidental Oman in 2011 as an HSE Specialist and work hard to make sure OXY & Contractors Operations are in comply with OXY and international health & safety regulations and guidelines. Has comprehensive experience of auditing and monitoring Industrial Safety Activities and maintain close liaison with clients, consultant, sub-contractors and local authorities during the construction, pre-commissioning, and commissioning phase of projects. Has an excellent experience in HSE data analyses and digitalization projects and programs.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Occidental Of Oman HSE Specialist

Feb 2011 -Present

Duties:

- Coordinates and support in the implementation of HSE Management and Emergency Management Systems, including program implementation, audits, inspections, contractor HSE program support and other HSE activities applicable to field operations
- Assist in the management of third-party audit vendors and support relationships i.e., Integrated Management System (IMS) for PAS 99 including ISO 45001, 39001, 14001 and 5001
- Leads Business Unit (BU) HSE Contractors scorecard system to monitor monthly Oxy and Contractors
 HSE performances (measuring the level of HSE compliance, the level of control measures implementation, and its effectiveness) for more than 70 Contractors
- Leads BU INTELX reporting and INET systems as super user
- Oversees BU Road Traffic tracking system.
- Development HSE score card project 2022- 2023 (Champion)
- Liaises with PACDA certification and licenses for the HQ building
- Leads BU Behavioral Base System
- Participates in planning and managing new HSE projects
- Liaises and conduct safety training and motivational programs related to the new hires
- Responds to any safety complaints and concerns raised by HQ employees
- Supports field locations on aspects related to HSE programs
- Liaises and support to update all HSE related digital dashboard data in OXY portal
- Represents OXY Oman at various HSE forums and meetings with various stakeholders and contractors
- Interacts with OXY Oman senior management and Oman government authorities on HSE matters
- Responds to any safety complaints and concerns raised by HQ employees
- Recommends solutions to issues, improvement opportunities or new prevention measures
- Conduct pre-job inspection on all operational equipment / vehicles to ensure compliance with safety and quality services requirement such as Pre-Start up Safety Reviews (PSSR)
- Conduct and participating health and hygiene inspections of OXY and contractors' facilities.
- Reports Accident / Incident to HSE team leader and entering the feedback / recommendation to Intelex System
- · Participates in Incident investigations and preparation of incident Investigation report.
- Assists with coordination and forward planning to ensure that all permit requirements are pre-

- planned one day before for next day's work, and ensures all required documentation accompanies requests for permits.
- HSE Data collection and analysis Gather, and validate HSE data from several department, ensuring data accuracy and integrity.
- Continuous improvement: Identify areas for improvement in HSE practices, processes, and systems based on data analysis. Collaborate with stakeholders to implement improvements and measure their impact on HSE performance
- Leads and reports the Scorecard report to OXY HSE Manager by evaluating all contractors with respect of HSE data reported by contractors and send OXY Monthly HSE KPI.
- Monitors/audits lock-out, tag-out system in relation to issued permits
- Participates in conducting Road Safety Spot Checks and present reports to HSE management and follow up with contractors to ensure closer of violations
- Supports and active member of firefighting team in case of emergency
- Ensure the efficient quality and effectiveness of risk assessment of specific operation
- Coordinates and assist with Operations Supervisor on all HSE concerns
- Maintains full compliance with OXY standards and procedures
- Supervises and checking all safety and work practices at the site. e.g., PPE, Safety Gears, Safety Signs
- Oversees checking, inspecting & calibrating multis gas testing instruments and H₂S personal detectors before its used and on monthly basis
- Responsible for co-ordinate with 3rd party suppliers of all kinds of gas testing instruments
- Responsible for follow up with contractors HSE representative for any type of HSE violation

Al Mansoori Production Services (Oman)

Duties:

QHSE Officer/Client is Petroleum Development Oman

Feb 2010 - Feb 2011

- Carrying risk assessments by undertaking regular checks and planned inspections at site.
- Provide and co-ordinate training for the drivers and other craft-based technicians as per company training matrix.
- Conduct regular safety inspection of site activities, plant, vehicles inspection, equipment, lifting equipment, scaffolding, electrical inspection, firefighting inspection etc.
- Conduct pre-job inspection on all operational equipment / vehicles to ensure compliance with safety and quality services requirement.
- Conduct camp inspection and report to HSEQ Manager.
- Conducting Audit as per the planned schedule for sub-contractors.
- Ensure the efficient quality and effective management system of risk assessment.
- Coordinate and assist the field Supervisor on all HSE and Quality assurance concerns.
- Provide a monthly HSEQ Performance report to the HSEQ Manager in addition provide analyses and report to the IVMS.
- To maintain full compliance with PDO contract HSEQ requirements.
- Supervising and checking all safety and work practices at the site. e.g., PPE, Safety Gears, Safety Signs.

Larsen & Toubro Electromech LLC (Oman)

Duties:

Jan 2007 - Feb 2010

- Disseminate and Communicate HSE Policies, HSE Management System requirements to site personnel
- Provide necessary advice, information, and support in the effective implementation of the HSEMS requirements and Contract HSE Plan
- Maintain close liaison with local authorities and client on HSE issues.
- Plan and conduct Internal HSE training programs, initiate drive to promote HSE awareness and performance.
- Providing relevant work procedure compliance information in weekly HSE meeting and related HEMP.
- Preparing Safe Work Procedure.
- Conduct regular safety inspection of site activities, Plant, Vehicles, Equipment, lifting equipment, Scaffolding, Electrical inspection, Firefighting inspection etc.

- Conduct Gas testing to ensure sufficient Oxygen level, Exposure limit, H₂S limit etc.
- Identify hazards and conduct risk assessment.
- Check hygiene condition at workplace.
- Ensure the strict adherence work permit during the shutdown stage / projects.
- Proper investigation and reporting of all accidents and near misses.
- Overall charge of the HSE related activities of the sites.
- Conduct HSE compliance Audit and Inspection during the project duration.
- Investigate incidents and serious HSE violations.
- Issue HSE Alerts for all reported medium & high potential incidents and near misses

PERSONAL AFFILIATIONS

Member of Oman Society Petroleum Services (OPAL).

SKILLS & ABILITIES

- Fluently speaking, writing, and reading Arabic & English
- Collaborative and accountable
- Excellent interpersonal and leadership skills
- Acts in line with appropriate core values, admits mistake and doesn't misrepresent myself for personal gain
- Ability to present information and produce reports
- Well versed with the health and safety standards defined by the regional and national regulatory bodies
- A quick learner with an ability to adapt new skills effectively
- Computer erudite with expertise in MS Office applications and other HSE programs
- Poised under pressure
- Ability to manage processes and/or projects

•

AWARDS

- Two (2) Grand Awards for Excellent Projects Achievements (OXY Awards).
- HSE Scorecard System Champion 2021/2022 (Development project) in 2023

ACADEMIC QUALIFICATIONS

- Bachelor's degree in Process Operation and Maintenance National University, 2019
- Technical Diploma in wiring electrician and overhead line.

PROFESSIONAL

- NEBOSH level 3 National Examination in Occupational Safety & Health
- NEBOSH Award in Health and Safety at Work level 2
- OSHA 30 hours
- IOSH (Institution in Occupational Safety and Health).
- ISO 45001:2018 (OHSMS)

INTERESTS

Travelling

REFERENCES

Available on request